<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://zejiachen9912.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://zejiachen9912.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-09-23T18:57:06+00:00</updated><id>https://zejiachen9912.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Zejia Chen - personal webpage &amp; blog </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Approaching Consulting from a Bayesian Lens</title><link href="https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2023/approaching-consulting-from-a-bayesian-lens/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Approaching Consulting from a Bayesian Lens"/><published>2023-09-11T14:30:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-11T14:30:16+00:00</updated><id>https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2023/approaching-consulting-from-a-bayesian-lens</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2023/approaching-consulting-from-a-bayesian-lens/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Bayes theorem quantifies and systematizes the idea of changing beliefs. So what can we learn from it when it comes to doing our day-to-day jobs?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Will AI Lead To Mass Unemployment</title><link href="https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2023/will-ai-lead-to-mass-unemployment/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Will AI Lead To Mass Unemployment"/><published>2023-08-14T02:50:15+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-14T02:50:15+00:00</updated><id>https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2023/will-ai-lead-to-mass-unemployment</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2023/will-ai-lead-to-mass-unemployment/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Navigating the Complex Future of Human-AI Interaction at work]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Animation and Its Relationship with Space</title><link href="https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2021/Animation-space-and-time/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Animation and Its Relationship with Space"/><published>2021-03-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-03-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2021/Animation-space-and-time</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2021/Animation-space-and-time/"><![CDATA[<p>The notion of space, a familiar yet obscure concept, is often taken for granted by us for its universal presence. It is almost axiomatic that space is a quintessential component of our life and almost all activities in which we conduct involved some sort of interaction with space. In the daytime, we travel through the physical space to desire destinations, while in the nighttime, we navigate an illusory space in our dream where the most far-fetched fantasies exist. Even the databased footprints, text messages, phone calls, and contacts, that we leave when scrolling through our phone are being stored in an abstract space in case we want to visit again.</p> <h3 id="space-role-in-cinema">Space Role in Cinema</h3> <p>Despite the imperative role that space plays to justify our understanding of the world, the notion of space is frequently regarded as the most basic vehicle to sustain characters and narrative in a fictional realm built by its creator. As a result, we see conventional film-makers use the space, like a backdrop, downplaying it to the extent that can be indistinguishably blended with other cinematic elements to prevent viewers digress from the major progression of the narrative.</p> <p>The appearance of animation, however, is deemed to overturn space’s neglected status and endow it with the capacity to draw connections to reality and crystalize the imaginative fantasy that cannot ever be imitated in live-action films. Aylish Wood, in her journal <a href="../../../assets/pdf/Re-animating Space.pdf">“Re-animating Space”</a> advocates viewers to re-examine space, rather than a vessel passively containing events and characters, as an entity itself, an unbridled stream that brings disparate elements together, portraying each movement in harmony. In this short essay, I will primarily focus on analyzing Wood’s idea of “approaching space as an entity” with the use of <i>The Adventures of Prince Ahmed</i> (Lotte Reiniger, 1926) as the primary example accompanied by some references of other films to illustrate how the notion of space typifies in the animated space. </p> <h3 id="the-adventures-of-prince-ahmed-groundbreaking-approach-to-space">The Adventures of Prince Ahmed Groundbreaking Approach to Space</h3> <p>The term “reverberation” that Woods brings forth is central to her theory of re-animating space - soliciting attention to the metamorphosis and the continuity that space brings about in cinema. “Reverberation of space,” an undergoing process that is “existing beyond the location of events, fluid and marked by heterogeneity, shifting between familiarity and uncertainty, and finally as chaotic and potentially unknowable.,”(29) can be identified as three distinct features — unexpectedness in transition/metamorphosis, heterogeneity in elements, and multiplicity in meaning, that each says something about animation’s ability to enliven space in a virtual realm.</p> <p>Aforementioned, space’s objectivity and accountability make it an apposite resort for viewers to rationalize the environment established by live-actions. We use space as a reference to locations and time in frames, and in return we justify the characters’ actions and motivations.</p> <p>To understand space as an independent body, however, Woods proposes a drastic shift from such conventional views and argues that space is, in essence, transformative and thus unexpected. Unlike conventional film-making which strives to maintain consistency between cuts of different spaces, animators have extensive latitude in manipulating and distorting space to achieve their whimsical ideas, playing with the viewer’s expectation in respect of the narrative. Boundaries between different dimensions are constantly being crossed and are interconnected through seamless action/graphic matches as we see in the opening four minutes of <i><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HW0v-NuudQw&amp;ab_channel=VaughnyBoi">Paprika</a></i> (Satoshi Kon, 2006) and the incessant metamorphosis of space and time in <i><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ed1RzYqgwqM&amp;ab_channel=NFB">The Street</a></i> (Caroline Leaf, 1976.)</p> <p>Such unexpected use of space, too, occurs in <em>The Adventures of Prince Ahmed</em>. In the prison where the African magician is captured, the space is initially a two-dimensional one with only the magician, being fully chained, despondently sitting on the ground. Although the general setting does not entail any clues of how he can escape from the claustrophobic cell, as the plot advanced, the frame starts transforming into a three-dimensional space, revealing the tiny window that is once obscurely situated at the back. The augmentation of the space’s dimension and the depth of fields offers an outlet for the magician’s escape, as he turns himself into a bat and ultimately flies out of the window after being informed about Prince Ahmed’s affair with Pari Banu.</p> <div class="l-body"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/taopa_1-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/taopa_1-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/taopa_1-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/taopa_1.png" data-zoomable=""/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/taopa_2-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/taopa_2-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/taopa_2-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/taopa_2.png" data-zoomable=""/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/taopa_3-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/taopa_3-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/taopa_3-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/taopa_3.png" data-zoomable=""/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The animation manipulates the background to show the way the magician escaped from prison </div> </div> <p>The perpetuating movement of space in both the recognizable and the concealed territories generates a sense of disorientation, inviting viewers to adjust and make connections between the spatial discontinuities. (30) </p> <h3 id="the-hybrid-nature-of-space">The Hybrid Nature of Space</h3> <p>Granted that the space should be treated as a sole entity, it is not to say that the existence of space is mutually exclusive, like a monolith that resists inclusion in other elements. Just the opposite, Woods asserts that space can be heterogeneous and fluid as well, quoting that the process of spatiality is “not simply to be the place of singular events, but an assembly of different habitations creating multifaceted spaces.”(32) It is at a triadic rapport with character and action that space fluidly ties disparate components unobtrusively. Woods ascribes the idiosyncratic film-making techniques as a cornerstone to construct fluid spatiality in animation.</p> <p>Similar to <a href="https://i.ytimg.com/an_webp/ed1RzYqgwqM/mqdefault_6s.webp?du=3000&amp;sqp=CL7EiacG&amp;rs=AOn4CLA5W14Umy5ryfxdBaWftsZUXJfgmQ">Caroline Leaf’s uses of sand and oil paint to intermingle with space and time</a>, <em>The Adventures of Prince Ahmed</em>’s rich visual language relies on Reiniger’s eminent scissor works, cutting paper into intricate silhouettes and using them for shadow puppetry. As the film is all told through shapes, the engagement with viewers is from the way that the characters and environments are cut out. Every figure is not only unique by its shapes, but also exhibits an illusion of texture where the cuts are so precious to bring out such details on the leaves, the feathers, and the outfits. What’s more, the cuts will go into the character to show their faces and facial expression, revealing what they are thinking at the moment. The subtlety of the figures’ movement further exemplifies the film’s close tie with space where they can move around in a broad and dramatized manner or in a small and barely noticeable way to present more in terms of the character’s psyche.</p> <div class="l-body"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/taopa_5-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/taopa_5-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/taopa_5-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/taopa_5.png" data-zoomable=""/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/taopa_4-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/taopa_4-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/taopa_4-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/taopa_4.png" data-zoomable=""/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The sequences of the fight between African Magician and Witch embodied by the delicate scissor works </div> </div> <p>On top of incorporating an exquisite art style, the film holds some seemingly violent scenes that also manifest the fluid spatiality. One of the scenes that focalize such characteristic is the fighting sequences where African Magician battles with the Witch as they transform into different creatures that have their own functions and how they can pose threats along with their use. While the ever-evolving shapes of the monsters offer an uncanny approach to illustrate a battle sequence, the shapes themselves implicitly impart shifting dynamic of the two’s duel as they strategically switch their forms to hold against another. </p> <h3 id="absence-of-space">Absence of Space</h3> <p>Although one may be entirely captivated by the labyrinthine filigree cutting that Reiniger creates, one aspect of <em>The Adventures of Prince Ahmed</em>’s twist of space to convey ideas lies in the absence of the space. Just as Woods encourages viewers to think about space when it is not “used-up,”(31) one would surprise to see how in-depth the figures are embodied in these two-dimensional black cutouts. Each character is considered an active, eloquent being when they move through the animated space, but at the same time, the silhouette animation leaves just enough space for our brain to supplement what is given, sparking new interpretation apropos of the scenarios presented.</p> <p>The theme of absence that we fill with our imagination in terms of what we see leads to Wood’s final point about the multiplicity stemming from the reverberation of space in which “a given spatial organization reconfigures space, forcing the re-discovery that what is mapped out through familiarity is only dimension of a multiplicity of possibilities.”(33) The aesthetic of <em>The Adventures of Prince Ahmed</em> is essentially a mix of realism and avant-garde abstraction. The special effects, like ocean waves, starlit skies, and most noticeably all the magic spells, play a crucial role to not only add physical layers (depth of field) onto the scene but bestow a metaphysical layer that is beyond our stereotypical world images.</p> <div class="l-body"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/taopa_6-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/taopa_6-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/taopa_6-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/taopa_6.png" data-zoomable=""/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The mythic light brings warmth and hope </div> </div> <p>Towards the end of the film, the witch lights up the magic lamp after a landslide victory over the devil. The emitting light, despite its intangibility, disseminates across the whole screen, bringing nothing but warmth and hope. Let alone a direct indication of a consummate finale, the lamp’s symbolic implication is salient in that it is an analogy of the pervasiveness of space, imbued with inspirational ideas and layers of meaning. In addition to the special effects, Reiniger’s deliberate employment of color (tinting/toning) to visually epitomize space as a boundless entity is equally sensational. Reminiscent of the visual language from German Expressionism, Reiniger injects color to planes in particular ways that form a prismatic relationship to the milieu of time and moods. The red or various shades of red could be an erotic scene or as a symbol of danger while blue may be a representation of nights. The vibrant color palette adds the finishing touch to the film’s mythical leitmotif, allowing viewers to not only see, but sense the multidimensionality of animated space. </p> <h3 id="final-words">Final Words</h3> <p>To finish, Woods recapitulates her idea in which “space seized upon by the imaginative possibilities of animation.”(45) We each experience reality and fantasy at the same time as individuals, and also collectively as a society. Reiniger’s evocative animation, just like the free-wheeling spatiality within, is an attempt to depict such phenomenon in silhouettes and fluid movements. In the course of almost a century, animation pushes our understanding of space and time in ways that are not considered viable in live-actions. Not just because its imaginative spirit, but through elastic approaches to engage with the audience — a unique way to move from the consciousness to the unconsciousness. </p>]]></content><author><name>Zejia Chen</name></author><category term="film"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An analysis of Aylish Wood's journal Re-animating Space, and how The Adventures of Prince Ahmed, the first animation ever created, realizes her thesis]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">To Sleep with Anger</title><link href="https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2021/to-sleep-with-anger/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="To Sleep with Anger"/><published>2021-03-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-03-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2021/to-sleep-with-anger</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2021/to-sleep-with-anger/"><![CDATA[<div class="l-body-outset"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/tswa_0-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/tswa_0-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/tswa_0-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/tswa_0.jpeg"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> In his neglected masterpiece <i>To Sleep with Anger</i> (Charles Burnett, 1990), Charles Burnett, in the unsung vanguard of African-American cinema, brings forth a slow-burning, soul-insinuating family drama that reflects African American’s assimilation and adjustment in a modern society. With no gangs, no drugs, and no intense violence involved, Burnett contrives a narrative that embodies the tension between urbanization and conservation through the portrayal of familial and ethnic bonds. </div> </div> </div> <h3 id="the-gideons">The Gideons</h3> <p>The story starts by sketching the lives of Gideon (Paul Butler) and Suzie (Mary Alice), a middle-class African American family of four that comes to reside in Los Angeles in the great migration from the deep south. As ostensibly peaceful as it appears, however, the conflict of the Gideon’s are already simmering at the beginning, indicated by the opening credits where Gideons’ is lighted up on fire, a seemingly allegory that suggests the internal struggles of the familial relationships and forebodes the invasion of the family’s traditional values.</p> <div class="l-body"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/tswa_1-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/tswa_1-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/tswa_1-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/tswa_1.png" data-zoomable=""/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/tswa_2-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/tswa_2-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/tswa_2-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/tswa_2.png" data-zoomable=""/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Gideon's dream of where he is on fire, a ominous sign of the dramatic strife that the family later encounters </div> </div> <p>The real conflict stems from the departure of the intrinsic idea of how to run a family between the older and younger generation. On the top of the family’s hierarchy is Gideon, a pious patriarch who holds strong religious, conservative values. Although physically in Los Angeles, a lot of his behaviors inherit traditions from the deep south. He has hens and greens farmed in the backyard, a habit that signifies his identity as a southerner, and he is vexed when he loses the toby, a charm given by his great-grandmother (and we will see later the destruction of the toby presages the misfortune which befalls on the family.) Gideon also possesses a strong sense of family unity in mind as he gets exasperated by his younger son Babe Brother’s (Richard Brooks) feckless parenthood and absence from Suzie’s birthday.</p> <div class="l-body"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/tswa_5-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/tswa_5-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/tswa_5-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/tswa_5.png" data-zoomable=""/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Giveon is superstitious and bears the same Southern beliefs just like Harry who later appears </div> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/tswa_4-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/tswa_4-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/tswa_4-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/tswa_4.jpeg" data-zoomable=""/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Babe Brother, on the other hand, lives in a modern family and bears modernized, progressive values </div> </div> </div> </div> <p>Standing against his father, Babe Brother, being caught up in America’s money fever with his ambitious wife, looks down on Gideon’s old-fashioned values. Not having realized that he is the most spoiled child, Babe Brother desperately disavows any associations with the family. He is anything but religious in that he does not ever accompany the family to church on Sunday; he eschews to take family responsibilities, like fixing the roof or feeding the hens, to alleviate the burden of his senescent parents. At the same time, Babe Brother is also (at least wants to be) an independent person. He discards the coeval African American stereotype and establishes himself as a successful, aspirational loan officer single-handedly. In the conversation with his wife Linda (Sheryl Lee Ralph) over his parenthood, Babe Brother shows contempt to his family’s past when Linda criticizes him as an indulged kid while fiercely arguing that he is no longer a “Babe” but a full-fledged adult. Hence, the primary conflict of the family centers around the dichotomy between Gideon and Babe Brother, with Junior (Carl Lumbly), the oldest son who adopts his father’s god-fearing ways, and Suzie, playing the mediator role, to conciliate the tension.</p> <h3 id="harrys-intrusion-tilts-the-balance">Harrys intrusion tilts the balance</h3> <p>The underlying hostile sentiment pervades in Gideon’s house and it is not until the unexpected visits from Harry (Danny Glover) who instigates chains of upheaval single-handedly. An old friend of Gideon’s from the earlier days back down south, Harry is welcomed by Gideon to stay in the house indefinitely. Although he carries a great mix of charm, Harry is full of tricks and duplicities. He plays a simple man while arcane phrases spilled out from his mouth; he is all about tradition, but honors himself as a modern man.</p> <p>After the Gideons sets off to church, Harry wanders in the house, inspecting the family’s personal belongings and familiarizing himself with each member’s history as if he is about to take charge of the place. Later, when Harry meets Babe Brother’s family, Burnett masterfully utilizes parallel cutting to further exemplify how Harry’s arrival precipitates the family’s latent conflict. As Harry’s nostalgic yet mythical southern folklores almost instantly mesmerize Babe Brother about the South, Burnett interpolates shots of the on-going baptism of Gideon’s grandchildren in the church. In one shot, the powerful, righteous gospel music reverberates around the chapel while in others, zany, apocryphal folktales perpetuate in Babe Brother’s mind. Such juxtaposition alludes to the exacerbating schism in the family, foreboding a series of inauspicious incidents as the film continues.</p> <div class="l-body"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/tswa_3-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/tswa_3-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/tswa_3-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/tswa_3.jpeg" data-zoomable=""/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The juxtaposition of the Gideons in the church for baptism and Harry's meander in the house </div> </div> <p>Like an emissary of the devil, Harry brings nothing but bad luck to the family, and things happen circumstantially to amplify the heretical, ominous vibe that comes with him. Linda picks up a card that seems like a sign of misfortune after Harry finishes his uncanny story ; the baby insides Pat (Vonetta McKee) kicks twice when Harry is about to greet her; most significantly, Gideon falls into a coma after an exhausting walk with Harry that reminds him of the affliction as an African American down south. Notwithstanding the turmoil that he spawns, Harry starts to take over the family as Gideon is fully disabled. One of the most disturbing scenes in the film is when Gideon finds out about his health issue the next morning. The red kettle, Gideon’s red pajama, and the red apple that Harry’s enjoying together emanate the menacing predicament that the family is about to face. At the moment that Suzie urges Gideon to go rest, worrying about his unstable health state, the scene cuts to Harry while he is slicing an apple to ingest using his knife, a symbol of threatened violence as Harry eviscerates the prey (Gideon) in front, tearing the family apart. </p> <h3 id="more-about-harrys-personality">More about Harrys personality</h3> <p>Harry is a peculiar person not only because of the demonic character that he embodies, but in that he represents the deep south in certain ways. Like a missionary, Black culture and southern superstitions come along when Harry first appears at the Gideon’s front door. Gideon and Suzie’s ebullient greeting does not dissipate Harry’s conservative beliefs. When Sunny (DeVaugh Walter Nixon), Gideon’s grandson, accidentally hits him with a broom, Harry is extremely offended since, according to the old tradition, that means bad luck. Forthwith, he spits in the broom and sprinkles salt over the shoulder as a resort to cast the misfortune away.</p> <div class="l-body"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/tswa_6-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/tswa_6-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/tswa_6-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/tswa_6.png" data-zoomable=""/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Harry's deep rooted southern superstitions was shown the second he enters Gideon's house </div> </div> <p>What’s more, Harry does not discard these morbid values but instead uses them to his advantage. During the party held by the Gideon’s, the corn liquor shared, the request of Hattie (Ethel Ayler) to sing a song from the old days, and the petrifying story of Emory and Hooker told are all tricks that Harry plays to rekindles people’s enthusiasm in memory of the South. Under his sway, Harry’s old buddies begin to imbibe the heterodox values that are instilled. When Gideon is on the verge of death, Okra’s (Davis Roberts) proposal ought to be the most ludicrous moment in the film. Okra has long been craved for Suzie. Seeing this time that Gideon’s malady might give him a chance to win over Suzie, he blatantly expresses his adoration to her, quoting the policy that she should be taken care of by one of Gideon’s lodge brothers and asking if he could be the first in line.</p> <p>By conscientiously incorporating each character with depth and richness, Burnett saturates <em>To Sleep with Anger</em>, a seemingly parable, with warring elements of African American traditions including progressive ideas versus old religions and rural idiosyncrasy versus urban respectability, depicting so vividly the destruction and the reconstruction of Gideon and Suzie’s family. </p>]]></content><author><name>Zejia Chen</name></author><category term="film"/><category term="AfricanAmerican-cinema"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An short analysis about the family dynamics and implications behind To Sleep with Anger, a representative work of the new African American cinema]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">High And Low</title><link href="https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2021/high-and-low/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="High And Low"/><published>2021-02-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2021/high-and-low</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2021/high-and-low/"><![CDATA[<div class="l-body-outset"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/hal_poster-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/hal_poster-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/hal_poster-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/hal_poster.png"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> Often regarded as the most “Western” of Japanese directors (Bordwell, 379), throughout his career, Akira Kurosawa had demonstrated to the world his illustrious aptitude for incorporating western culture into his films to create a distinct cinematic language both stylistically and symbolically. While many of his antecedent films, such as <i>Rashomon</i> (1950) and <i>Throne of Blood</i> (1957), epitomized his keen assimilation of classic western literature and philosophical ideas, in <i>High and Low</i> (Akira Kurosawa, 1963) Kurosawa showed off his superb mastery of cinematography, mise-en-scene, and editing in translating character’s psychology and implicit meanings unobtrusively, making it truly a film of its time. </div> </div> </div> <p><em>High and Low</em> can be demarcated into two very different but both equally phenomenal halves. The first act is a seemingly theatrical drama that follows Gondo (Mifune Toshiro), a business executive at a shoe company whose chauffeur’s son is kidnapped in place of his own in the midst of his ambitious leveraged buyout in gaining control of the corporation.</p> <h3 id="a-farcical-extortion">A Farcical Extortion</h3> <p>Although the first half of the film’s narrative is entirely set in a single space - Gondo’s resplendent mansion, it does not prevent Kurosawa from portraying each character’s internal emotions through appropriate blocking and frame composition. Having realized that it is the chauffeur’s son (Shimazu Masahiko) who ended up missing, in the frame where Gondo is about to answer the call from the kidnapper (Yamazaki Tsutomu) with the chauffeur (Sada Yutaka), the assistant (Mihashi Tatsuya) and the chief detective (Ishiyama Kenjiro) surrounding him, Kurosawa aptly employs blocking to embody their inner psychology that is congruous with their characteristics.</p> <p>Gondo, the main figure who is responsible for paying the ransom, is placed in the foreground of the image, while Aoki, the most agitating one, is in the back center yearning for any possible information that may keep his son from danger. Such spatial relationships present the two central figures to the conflicts, and, at the same time, accentuate the power hierarchy between the two. Gondo is the one who overrules everything, as he is exercising his agency in answering the call, yet Aoki, a menial salaryman who is not relevant to any negotiations, is held off at a distance.</p> <p>Two remaining characters are also deliberately placed to not only fill up the frame but also reveal their motivations. From the beginning, we have already known that Kawanishi (the assistant) is working in collusion with Gondo’s business rival to go against him. Hence, we can clearly see how Kawanishi’s position in the frame is consonant with his motivation as he situates at the left corner away from the other three, poking his neck to clandestinely spy for any exploitable intel without explicitly interfering the main action. On the opposite side of Kawanishi is the chief detective, another main figure of the film who aims to rescue the kid without jeopardizing Gondo’s assets. Unlike Kawanishi, he sits just in between Gondo and Aoki, striving to resolve the primary conflict. By spacing each individual in these specific positions, the character’s natural behavior evinces the nature of their behavior, which is why Kurosawa is considered a master of incorporating mise-en-scene to bestow another layer of meanings upon the surface.</p> <div class="l-body"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/hal_1-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/hal_1-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/hal_1-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/hal_1.png" data-zoomable=""/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> A single shot is enough to capture each character's inner psychology and the power dynamics in between </div> </div> </div> </div> <h3 id="the-theatrical-aspect-of-high-and-low">The Theatrical Aspect of <em>High and Low</em></h3> <p>Right in the next scene, combined with orchestrated character movement and punctilious editing, Kurosawa again exhibits his deep understanding of implementing stylistic devices to gain control over the plot progression.</p> <p>When Gondo picks up the phone, rather than letting the viewer wait and see what exactly the kidnapper has to offer, the narrative fasts forward to later where everyone has gotten together to review the kidnapper’s words in the living room, forming another spectacular scene that captures each individual’s reaction and psyche in response to the moral conundrum. At the beginning of the scene, as the chief detective starts to play the recording, an establishing shot of the room is displayed to portray every person’s close attention to the kidnapper’s response (shot 1). Being notified about the abductor’s perverse demand, Gondo, who initially sits beside his family, gradually walks toward the back away from the crowd, realizing that he must now make a difficult choice between the boy and his company (shot 2).</p> <p>In the next second, however, the scene quickly cuts to a new frame where Gondo and Aoki, in parallel with each other, both contemplate where the crisis will end up going (shot 3). Aoki, having no control over the situation and facing forward anxiously, is hoping Gondo is kind enough to pay the ransom and save his son. Gondo, on the other hand, is more inclined to not pay the ransom for the sake of his company, but also he feels guilty for his indifference as he faces backward, avoiding taking on any responsibilities. The empty space in between, like an unmade decision, lingers, just as we are waiting to see how the quandary can be ultimately resolved.</p> <div class="l-body"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/hal_2-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/hal_2-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/hal_2-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/hal_2.png" data-zoomable=""/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> shot 1 </div> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/hal_3-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/hal_3-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/hal_3-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/hal_3.png" data-zoomable=""/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> shot 2 </div> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/hal_4-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/hal_4-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/hal_4-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/hal_4.png" data-zoomable=""/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> shot 3 </div> </div> </div> </div> <p>Then, just when the kidnapper continues with his threat, Gondo begins to move further back into the frame, as a symbol of deep compunction when hearing his assertion for not paying the ransom over the phone. At the same time, his assistant at the left corner leaves the seat in an attempt to calm him down. Forthwith, the camera again cuts to the same poison ditto (shot 4), but with Gondo, Aoki, and Kawanishi positioning themselves in relation to each other. Being informed by Gondo’s rejection, the distance between Gondo and Aoki stretches to a greater extend, connoting the dichotomy between their self-interest. Yet, as Kawanishi walks toward Gondo, his entrance to the frame breaks the equilibrium. Now, Gondo and Kawanishi are on the left side while Aoki is being left out at the right corner. Such unbalanced frame composition signifies Gondo’s strong propensity for not paying the ransom at the moment.</p> <p>After the abductor hangs up the phone, the scene cuts back to the previous establishing shot (shot 5), but now with Gondo situates at the back of the center and Kawanishi covers up the empty space he left, saturating the frame to its fullest. Throughout the sequence, Kurosawa consciously utilizes the multiple-camera system and the editing to maneuver the entire scene from different vantage points, magnifying the main characters’ troubled states meanwhile “allowing the actors to play the entire scene without any interruptions.” (Bordwell, 380)</p> <div class="l-body"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/hal_5-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/hal_5-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/hal_5-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/hal_5.png" data-zoomable=""/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> shot 4 </div> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/hal_6-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/hal_6-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/hal_6-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/hal_6.png" data-zoomable=""/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> shot 5 </div> </div> </div> </div> <h3 id="kurosawa-and-time">Kurosawa and Time</h3> <p>Kurosawa’s eminent cinematic language does not just manifest through his manipulation of space, but time as well.</p> <p>Although the narrative in the first half of the film is seemingly linear, it does not prevent him to put small twists to advance the plot. Kurosawa uses the tape recorder as a device to handle the narrative progression. From the scene aforementioned, we have already seen how he advances the plot by skipping Gondo and the kidnapper’s phone call and cutting to the recording directly. In the scene where Gondo and the police are preparing for the ransom delivery the next day. Kurosawa once more employs the tape recorder as a medium to play with the narrative. According to the previous plot, we know that, in the morning, the kidnapper promises to think through Gondo’s offer that he will only pay the ransom after first seeing the boy alive. Shortly after, however, the scene has already cut to the evening as the police are preparing the ransom (shot 6), not letting us have any information about the kidnapper’s response yet. It is not until later when the chief detective begins to play the recording, that we then get to be notified apropos of the train delivery and the police’s ploy.</p> <p>Another detail worths noticing is at the end of the first act when Gonda picks up his training as an apprentice to hide the powder inside the suitcase for tracking the kidnapper down . Gondo, sitting at the golden ratio spot of the frame, is tweaking the suitcase while others respectively put their works aside, standing upright to pay reverence to his great sacrifice. By carefully staging each character’s position and arranging their movement, Kurosawa is able to direct our eyes to where we exactly need to. The extreme contrast of Gondo sitting with everyone else standing also signifies Gondo’s downfall as he mocks “It’s like I’m starting over already.” (shot 7)</p> <div class="l-body"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/hal_7-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/hal_7-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/hal_7-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/hal_7.png" data-zoomable=""/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> shot 6 </div> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/hal_8-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/hal_8-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/hal_8-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/hal_8.png" data-zoomable=""/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> shot 7 </div> </div> </div> </div> <h3 id="final-thought">Final Thought</h3> <p>The extraordinary thing about <em>High and Low</em> though is that it does not just focus the narrative on a one man’s drama. In Japanese, the film’s title is closer to Heaven and Hell, but the English title High and Low works appositely with Kurosawa’s theme. It is a story about wealth and property, hope and despair, good and evil. Unlike most of Kurosawa’s samurai epics which embody a clear boundary of right and wrong, <em>High and Low</em> is full of contrast and ambivalence. Is the kidnapper’s motif purely stemmed from jealousy? Is the fact that Gondo decides to pay the ransom due to a sudden epiphany or from his intention to collect sympathy from the public? Is it ethical for the police to postpone the apprehension just for the sake of getting the death sentence on the kidnapper that wind up causing another woman’s life? At the end of the day, there are no definitive answers to these questions, and Kurosawa leaves them to our own interpretation.</p>]]></content><author><name>Zejia Chen</name></author><category term="film"/><category term="Japanese-cinema"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A close examination of Akira Kurosawa's mastery in cinematography and mise-en-scene]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">French New Wave and the Francois Truffaut’s legacy</title><link href="https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2021/shoot-the-piano-player/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="French New Wave and the Francois Truffaut’s legacy"/><published>2021-02-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2021/shoot-the-piano-player</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2021/shoot-the-piano-player/"><![CDATA[<div class="l-body-outset"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/stpp_1-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/stpp_1-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/stpp_1-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/stpp_1.jpeg"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> The French New Wave, in general, was about both iconoclasm and reverence for the long-lasting film traditions. If the fragmentary editing epitomized by jarring jump cuts, and the extended long takes consisted of medley montages in New Wave films were a testimony against the institutionalized cinema, then, the adoption and references of antecedent film movements and genres were the most sincere accolade to early art-cinemas from the New Wave directors.  </div> </div> </div> <p><em>Shoot the Piano Player</em> (Francois Truffaut, 1960), Truffaut’s second feature film may on the surface level may feel like a modest tale of crime thriller centering on pianist Charlie’s (Charles Aznavour) entanglement in a bizarre cat-and-mouse game. However, it is full of intimation and little eccentricities worthy of the viewers’ attention, crystalizing the spirit of the French New Wave. </p> <h3 id="the-new-wave-in-action">The New Wave in Action</h3> <p>It is often noted how many of the directors within the New Wave made references to classic film movements and genres; so did Truffaut. For instance, the claustrophobic atmosphere stemmed from the chiaroscuro lighting schemes, and the dramatic shadow patterning right at the opening of the film is his direct tribute to the classic American noir films (1:50). Yet, this 4-min sequence is full of Truffaut’s acute implementation of salient New Wave stylistic elements. The scene starts with a chase sequence displaying Chico (Albert Remy) running for life from the two gangsters (Daniel Boulanger, Claude Mansard) pursuing. The interposition of shots of Chico sprinting and the car following with disoriented camera movements are the distinct language of the New Wave directors who knowingly twist temporal and spatial continuity. At the same time, Truffaut adopts the nonlinear storyline from neorealist films to play with the narrative a bit. While the viewers are still fixated on the thrilling chase sequence, in the next second Chico is stunned by a streetlight and soon gets rescued by a stranger (Alex Joffe) just passing by (2:37). Rather than return to Chico’s escape, for the next two minutes, the narrative digresses instead to capture Chico and the stranger having a casual conversation about life, love, and marriage. It is not until the stranger disappears at the corner (and never reappears in the rest of the film), the chase again carries on.</p> <div class="l-body"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/stpp_2-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/stpp_2-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/stpp_2-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/stpp_2.jpeg" data-zoomable=""/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/stpp_3-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/stpp_3-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/stpp_3-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/stpp_3.jpeg" data-zoomable=""/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/stpp_4-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/stpp_4-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/stpp_4-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/stpp_4.jpeg" data-zoomable=""/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The chase scene digresses to the small talk between Chico and the stranger </div> </div> <p>Still, the innovative editing and the episodic narrative structure are just one snippet of cinematic elements that Truffaut utilizes in <em>Shoot the Piano Player</em>. Followed by the wildly acclaimed debut The 400 Blows (Francois Truffaut, 1959), Truffaut continued to masterfully maneuver the frame to draw audiences’ attention to a specific point in the scene. In the final snowbound shootout with the gangsters (79:00), Lena (Marie Dubois) gets accidentally shot at on her way looking for Charlie. When Charlie finally shows up, everything is too late as Lena, covered in snow, has lost her breath already. As Charlie holds Lena with remorse, rather conventionally cut to a close-up of Lena’s face, Truffaut employs a combination of zoom shot and freeze-frame to immortalize this poignant moment, magnifying Charlie’s anguish in losing the beloved one. </p> <h3 id="injections-of-drollery">Injections of Drollery</h3> <p>Truffaut takes the free-wheeling side of the French New Wave further by implementing gentle humor into his film even if the tone and subject matters can be quite intense. In the scene where Charlie and Lena have been kidnapped by the gangsters, for example, Truffaut turns a supposed agitated maneuver with the criminals into a waggish slapstick (25:30). Despite being kidnapped, Charlie and Lena keep having discussion apropos of driving, women, and sex with the two gangsters along the way, as if they have known each other for a long time. Then, noticing that the two gangsters have let down their guards, Lena pushes her foot on the drivers’s pedal in an attempt to get the car pulled over. The tactic is successful, allowing Charlie and Lena to walk away with ease while the gangsters have to end the kidnapping to deal with a passing traffic policeman. Interpolating these humorous aspects within the story again emphasizes the versatility and playfulness of this film alone.</p> <p>Sometimes <em>Shoot the Piano Player</em> becomes reflexive as Truffaut reflects on the making of the film and makes flippant remarks about it. In an erotic scene where Charlie is about to enjoy himself for the rest of the night as Clarisse (Michele Mercier), already naked, is lying next to him (20:58), Charlie takes the bedsheet to cover Clarisse’s breast, joking “This is how it’s done in the movies.” Just like that, Truffaut, in sleight of hand, integrates his jocular comment about the classic Hollywood’s finicky Production Code, evincing his attitude towards the need for modern movies to disregard any forms of restriction.</p> <div class="l-body"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/stpp_5-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/stpp_5-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/stpp_5-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/stpp_5.png"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> my favorite scene in <i>Shoot the Piano Player</i> </div> </div> </div> </div> <h3 id="truffauts-brilliance">Truffaut’s Brilliance</h3> <p>Besides, Truffaut did not apply all the cinematic elements of the French New Wave just for the sake of applying it; what really appeals to him in making the film is the sense of loneliness and alienation that is suggested for the protagonist. Charlie, a passe classical pianist, is portrayed as a diffident and reticent person who seems to be a little bit cut off from the rest of the world. In order to reflect such personality appropriately, Truffaut makes use of many New Wave stylistic devices, along with voiceovers and flashbacks, guiding the viewers into Charlie’s psyche. The voiceover is the most frequent and effective device that sheds light on Charlie’s subjective thoughts throughout the film. In particular, in the sequence where Charlie accompanies Lena back home right off the work (15:30), the close-ups of Charlie’s hand seeking to hold Lena’s is juxtaposed with shots of his restrained face. Such thoughtful editing is an apposite representation of Charlie’s lack of courage in taking initiatives, exemplifying his agitated state at the moment. The subsequent voiceover of Charlie searching for improvisations to break the silence once again directly demonstrates to the viewer Charlie’s reserved character.</p> <div class="l-body"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/stpp_6-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/stpp_6-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/stpp_6-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/stpp_6.png"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Montage of increasingly close-up shots to embody Charlie's unsettlement when it comes to audition </div> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/stpp_7-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/stpp_7-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/stpp_7-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/stpp_7.png"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> The camera stays with the young woman after Charlie entering the audition room </div> </div> </div> </div> <p>Another brilliant example of Truffaut’s keen link of visual style with the story’s idea and characterizations is the audition scene. Truffaut deliberately utilizes montage to call attention to Charlie’s psychology. As Charlie walks across the corridor and about to enter the audition room (33:53), first a medium close-up of Charlie playing with the door key is shown. Forthwith, we get three different close-ups of his finger teasing the door bell within different scales, and then a long shot from the end of the hall which completely jolts us back out again. The montage of Charlie’s hesitant actions plus the elongated corridor scene reinforce the idea of hollowness, as his ambivalent behavior keeps haunting him.</p> <p>What’s more scintillating is that, in the next shot, the door is opened by a young lady who has just finished her audition. In most cases, we would expect the camera to follow Charlie entering the audition room and watching him performing in front of the judges. Surprisingly, the camera instead stays with this young lady, tracking back with her as she walks through the corridor and out of the building. Such an open-ended sequence epitomizes Truffaut’s mastery of the incidental narrative structure, and makes us wonder about his ulterior motif in creating it. Is he showing the lady because she might just be another victim of the sexual harassment just like Charlie’s dead wife, or because he simply wants to? By conscientiously incorporating stylistic features from the New Wave, meanwhile, blending his uptake of the modern cinema, Truffaut in harmony, creates an idiosyncratic film language that is distinct from any other coeval peers.</p>]]></content><author><name>Zejia Chen</name></author><category term="film"/><category term="new-wave"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An investigation about The French New Wave and how its innovative, iconoclastic styles epitomizes in Francois Truffaut's Shoot the Piano Player]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Early Soviet Montage Movement</title><link href="https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2020/soviet-montage/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Early Soviet Montage Movement"/><published>2020-12-20T15:46:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-20T15:46:00+00:00</updated><id>https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2020/soviet-montage</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2020/soviet-montage/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="introduction">Introduction</h3> <p>During the Montage movement, Soviet films were relatively similar in terms of genres. As Lenin declared, “Of all the arts, for us the cinema is the most important,” (Bordwell, 107) The Bolshevik regime realized that the cinema was the most powerful tool for propaganda and education, given the 80% rates of illiteracy and the mix of vernaculars straddled across the country. Hence, we could see a great similarity in films directed by most of the Montage directors during that time. Depictions of uprisings, strikes, and rebellion against the authoritarian regime were extremely popular among directors who emphasized the Bolshevik ideology in films.</p> <p>Both <em>Battleship Potemkin</em> (Eisenstein, 1925) and <em>Mother</em> (Pudovkin, 1926) include various strikes and demonstration sequences to highlight the tension between the authorities and civilians, commemorating the failed Revolution of 1905. In order to be as comprehensible to the viewers as possible, intertitles in both <em>Mother</em> and <em>Battleship Potemkin</em> were simple and concise. Phrases like “It was spring”, “Even a dog wouldn’t eat this”, and “Brothers!” helped to maintain the continuity in the narratives, but also powerful enough to evoke the spectator’s emotion about the Bolsheviks’ solidarity in the revolution.</p> <h3 id="pudovkin-and-eisenstein">Pudovkin and Eisenstein</h3> <h4 id="pudovkin">Pudovkin</h4> <p>As Bordwell points out in Film History, “…it [montage] also served more abstract purposes, linking two actions for the sake of a thematic point.” (117) The use of montage to construct narrative and court spectators’ attention was prevalent among Soviets directors, and Pudovkin and Eisenstein are prime examples. Despite their consensus on the search for dynamism through montage, Pudovkin and Eisenstein, however, diverged drastically regarding the role which montage played in film narration. Greatly influenced by Kuleshov, Pudovkin inherited the idea of continuity editing from Hollywood, in which filmmaker created an immersive experience for the viewer to match reality in a natural way. Pointed out by Pudovkin in his Selected Essays, “The director despotically manipulate the viewer’s attention. The viewer sees only what the director shows him”(35). He stressed the use of montage to achieve the “the maximum simplicity”(36) and “clarity in resolving each individual problem”(36) when constructing a sequence.</p> <p>In the first sequence of <em>Mother</em>, when the mother (Vera Baranovskaya) is being abused by the alcoholic husband (Aleksandr Chistyakov), Pudovkin employed techniques like match-on-action and eye-line matches to cut between numerous shots to highlight each protagonist’s personality, but also intelligibly establish the family dynamics with little explanation. The back-and-forth cuts of father and the son (Nikolay Batalov) and respective close-ups of the hammer and the father’s clenched hands, captures the family’s extreme tension and the son’s resolution to protect his mother. Reminiscent of the last-minute rescue sequence in <em>The Birth of a Nation</em> (D. W. Griffith, 1915), the crosscutting between the prison riot and the protest march in the last sequence of <em>Mother</em>, helps to build up the final culmination, and captivate the audience’s attention in a state of intense excitement.</p> <div class="l-body"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/sm_1-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/sm_1-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/sm_1-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/sm_1.jpg"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> <i>Mother</i> </div> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/sm_2-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/sm_2-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/sm_2-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/sm_2.jpg"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> The Kuleshov Effect employed in the first sequence of <i>Mother</i> </div> </div> </div> </div> <h4 id="eisenstein">Eisenstein</h4> <p>Rather than paying excessive attention to maintain a comprehensible narrative like Pudovkin, Eisenstein was more radical and more experimental in terms of what montage could achieve. In his theory of film, Eisenstein often brought up the term “conflict” in which “antithetical elements clash and produce a synthesis that goes beyond both.” (Bordwell, 113) Eisenstein did not see montage as a resort to maintain a clear temporal and spatial relationship, guiding the spectator through the entire narrative. Rather he envisioned each individual shot or sequence as if it was a puzzle with meanings of their own. When combined, however, these individual shots created an utterly different picture, sparking new meaning that was not present in either of the original shots.</p> <p>The infamous Odessa stairs sequence in <em>Battleship Potemkin</em> is the moment when Eisenstein fully actualizes his “intellectual montage” theory. Shots of soldiers marching down steps symbolize an oppressive force juxtaposed with unarmed civilians fleeing, barring the straightforward indication of the helplessness of the Russian people, offers new meanings of the Russian Empire’s forces’ brutality. The last sequence of the Odessa massacre constitutes shots of the stroller sliding downstairs across dead bodies, the slaughter of civilians, and close-ups of a woman’s face, covered with blood. Albeit the considerable lack of spatial and temporal relation, the sequence’s short and sharp intercuts epitomize the agony of innocuous civilians, insinuating the viciousness of the Russian army. Besides, Eisenstein deliberately intercuts three consecutive shots of stone lion statues when illustrating the bombardment of the Odess theater. Although shots of the lion may not mean much on their own, when combined, it seems like the lion is rising from its sleep. They signify the Odessa people waking up and fighting against the totalitarian regime and seemingly paralleled with the first half of the film, where asleep crews ignite the revolution on battleship Potemkin. </p> <div class="l-body"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/sm_3-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/sm_3-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/sm_3-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/sm_3.jpg"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> The Odessa Stairs sequence </div> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/sm_4-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/sm_4-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/sm_4-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/img4film/sm_4.jpeg"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> The lion montage displayed in the <i>Battleship Potemkin</i> </div> </div> </div> </div> <h3 id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h3> <p>At the beginning of the 1930s, audiences, who were tired of the esoteric style of montage, began to demand for something more accessible and more evocative. Along with the permeation of series of Socialist Realism films which focus on realistic stories that supported Communist values, the Soviet Montage movement eventually came to an end. Like many revolutionary cinema movements, however, techniques by the Soviet Montage filmmakers continue to influence movies, such as <em>Rear Window</em> (Alfred Hitchcock, 1954) and <em>The Godfather</em> (Francis Ford Coppola, 1972), to this day.</p>]]></content><author><name>Zejia Chen</name></author><category term="film"/><category term="Soviet-cinema"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A brief discussion about early Soviet montage movement & comparisons of montage employment between Pudovkin and Eisenstein]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bicycle Thieves &amp;amp; De Sica’ episodic narrative structure</title><link href="https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2020/bicycle-thieves/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bicycle Thieves &amp;amp; De Sica’ episodic narrative structure"/><published>2020-12-06T19:46:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-06T19:46:00+00:00</updated><id>https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2020/bicycle-thieves</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2020/bicycle-thieves/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="introduction">Introduction</h3> <p>In his essay about <em>Bicycle Thieves</em> (De Sica, 1948), Andre Bazin makes a jocular comment in terms of the film’s simple narrative, “Plainly there is not enough material here even for a news item: the whole story would not deserve two lines in a stray-dog column.” (Bazin, 50) Indeed when examining the entire film, <em>Bicycle Thieves</em> seemingly advances in chronological order, telling a story of Antonio Ricci (Lamberto Maggiorani), an unemployed man desperately searching for his stolen bike in a two-day span. However, De Sica, in both the uses of linear and episodic narrative structures, earnestly create one of the most wondrous and heart-rending masterpieces, portraying the vicissitude of a person living in post-WWII Italy.</p> <h3 id="a-simple-story-about-father-and-son">A Simple Story about Father and Son</h3> <p>In the majority of Hollywood productions, the characters in film often have sets of goals or deadlines (this is often called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Continuity_editing">continuous editing</a>). All the events that occur in the film are designed to advance the plot to meet these goals and achieve a consummate finale. The same logical narrative structure also applies to <em>Bicycle Thieves</em>. Like the film title suggests, the whole film’s narrative settles around the bicycle. Throughout the film, Ricci’s actions and behaviors are mostly driven by his motivation to recover his beloved bicycle. And we can see a clear linear causal logic in the narrative structure just at the beginning, establishing the cause and setting the goal of the film.   </p> <p>As the film starts, we follow a medium shot of a bus stopping by the unemployment office with a crowd of job seekers rushing to the gate, longing for the slightest chance of securing a position. Along with the movement of a worker leaving the crowd yelling for Ricci, the scene is cut to a panoramic shot, establishing the temporal space surrounded for the first time . Despite having lost faith in job searching, Ricci is fortuitous enough to procure a job of pasting posters among the massive unemployed, but a bicycle is a requisite to secure the position. Henceforth, a dissolve transition leads us to the next scene, where Ricci is walking backed home with his wife, Maria (Lianella Carell), informing her about the dilemma he faces. Considering that it is a luxury for Ricci to secure a job, notwithstanding the indigent status, they decide to sell their bedsheets to earn the money for the bike. Just as Maria begins to wash the sheets and getting them ready to impawn, at the very next shot, the scene has already dissolved to the pawnshop where Maria is bargaining with the staff, begging to trade the sheets for a better price.</p> <div class="l-body"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/bt_1-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/bt_1-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/bt_1-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/bt_1.jpg"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> The tilted shot of the pawn shop filled with used bedsheets signifies the impoverished condition of post-WWII Italy </div> </div> </div> </div> <p>With all the sacrifices, Ricci finally gets what he has dreamed of, a bicycle that allows him to support his family of four. With his beloved bicycle, in the next sequence, Ricci arrives forthwith at the employment office to register to be an official poster hanger. From firstly securing the job, and being notified about the prerequisite, to the family having to trade the bedsheets for the bicycle, until finally Ricci acquires the job in the employment office, the very beginning of <em>Bicycle Thieves</em> rigorously follows a <strong>linear, causal narrative structure</strong>. In a mere 10 minutes length, De Sica adapts continuous editing to outline the general context of Ricci and his bicycle in a logical and succinct manner.</p> <h3 id="the-episodic-narrative-takes-over">The episodic narrative takes over</h3> <p>It is ostensibly a simple plot if we only choose to look at the first 20 minutes of <em>Bicycle Thieves</em>. However, as Ricci’s bike is stolen and he starts the fruitless search, the episodic approach to story-telling, from time to time, supplants the causal narrative as an alternative mean to advance the narrative till the end. “The film unfolds on the level of accident” (Bazin, 59). Bazin’s words shed light on the involuntary nature of De Sica’s episodic narration. The hopeless search of the father and the son (Enzo Staiola) happens very naturally, as they meandering in the city of Rome with no particular destinations in mind. The film takes us to multiple spots through the two’s search: the union gathering, the police station, the spare parts market, the seer, and the church, some are for the sake of looking for the stolen bike while others are virtually out of spontaneity. Nonetheless, we are forced to follow the lens to observe, to feel the tension and the struggle of the bottom of the society without the film explicitly spelling it out for the audience. </p> <p>The scene where Ricci and Bruno shelter from the rain is a classic exemplar of De Sica’s dedramatized approach to the narrative. Just as Ricci and Bruno are on the way to another spare parts market, a pouring rain interrupts their miserable search. Several long shots firstly illustrate them standing in the rain at a loss, as people and vendors are fleeing for shelter. Then the scene cuts to the close-up shots, as Ricci wandering, keeping Bruno by his side, anxiously looking for any possible traces of his stolen bike. Just when the rain gets heavier and heavier, in despair, Ricci and Bruno decide to halt the search momentarily and shelter under a roof. A span of 2-minutes shelter scene begins with a brief conversation between the two about Ricci’s inadvertent behavior to his son. Then, out of nowhere, a group of foreign seminarians comes to the roof for shelter. They speak an utterly different language (there are not any subtitles given). Interestingly, however, De Sica did not immediately cut to the next scene where the rain is already over. Instead, we are just as trapped and confused as Ricci and Bruno, being forced to spend time listening to the querulous chatters till the rain is over.</p> <div class="l-body"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/bt_2-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/bt_2-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/bt_2-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/bt_2.jpeg"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> An random encounter with seminarians seemingly adds no constructive advancement to the plot but is indeed how life sometimes unfolds </div> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/bt_3-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/bt_3-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/bt_3-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/bt_3.jpeg"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> The back and forth shot between the rich and Bruno </div> </div> </div> </div> <p>Another salient example of De Sica’s brilliant episodic narration is the restaurant scene. After an irresponsible reprimand to Bruno and having feared that he has drowned, Ricci finally realizes his obliviousness to his son that all this time his focus is just to find the bicycle, because of how much the it means to him. To make up for the previous impropriety, Ricci promises Bruno to have a feast and go home afterward, forgetting about the search for a moment. When Ricci and Bruno walk into a restaurant, they order mozzarellas and wine as if it is a celebration. It seems like Ricci decides to move on and the story again is heading toward a positive direction. However, Ricci and Bruno are accidentally assigned to a table right next to an opulent family who is having a feast. The multiple back-and-forth cuts of the family’s gluttony as oppose to their simple courses set as a constant remainder to Ricci the indispensable role that money plays in reality. Being pulled back from the fantasy, Ricci realized that the bicycle is the last and only resort to make his family eat again, and he is going to take any means necessary to retrieve it.</p> <h3 id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h3> <p>When an American producer told Zavattini that “Hollywood film would show a plane passing overhead, then machine-gun fire, then the plane falling out of the sky but that a Neorealist film would show the plane passing once, then again, then again,” Zavattini replied “It is not enough to have the plane pass by three times; it must pass by twenty times” (T&amp;B, 325). Unlike <em>Bicycle Thieves</em>’s heavy emphasis on the episodic and accidental narrative structure, classical Hollywood productions, like <em>Casablanca</em> (Michael Curtiz, 1942), relied on frequent cuttings and editing to downplay the episodic elements. In doing so, the film can put the focus on the main cause of the story, avoiding any possible distractions and impediments and ultimately offering audiences the perceived perfect ending.</p> <p>“The (search) events are not necessarily signs of something, of a truth of which we are to be convinced, they all carry their own weight, their complete uniqueness, that ambiguity that characterizes any fact”(Bazin, 52). Just as Bazin suggested, by cleverly adding independent accidents along the narrative, it is ambiguous in terms of what exact message <em>Bicycle Thieves</em> wants to send to the audiences. Some audiences might be drawn into the film’s indictment for inequality which permeates the post-WW2 Italian society, while others are affected by the in-depth portrait of father-son power dynamics or the trenchant depiction of religion’s sanctimoniousness. <strong>But does it matter? At the end, when Ricci and Bruno disappear into the masses, their story has become part of our story. And what we might see as something personal has become universal.</strong></p>]]></content><author><name>Zejia Chen</name></author><category term="film"/><category term="Italian-neorealism"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A short analysis on the episodic narrative structure of the classic Italian Neorealists film - Bicycle Thieves]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thoughts on &quot;Cinemas of Attraction&quot;</title><link href="https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2020/cinema-of-attraction/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thoughts on &quot;Cinemas of Attraction&quot;"/><published>2020-11-16T22:56:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-16T22:56:00+00:00</updated><id>https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2020/cinema-of-attraction</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2020/cinema-of-attraction/"><![CDATA[<p>In the essay “The Cinema of Attraction,” Gunning made a clear distinction between early theatrical cinema and early narrative films using 1906 as the defining year. He argued that instead of focusing on cinema as a medium that conveyed a sense of logical narratives, early films (prior to 1906) were simply created as a tool for amusements and novelties, which he later defined as “the cinema of attractions.”</p> <p>Inspired by Eisenstein’s “Montage of Attractions” essay, Gunning believed that attractions provoked spectators’ sensual and psychological reactions. The prime goal of early cinema is to proffer such magical illusions to the broad audiences, and all the cinematography and editing techniques utilized (tricks) are for the sole intention to solicit such attention out of them.</p> <p>Gunning credited two significant utilization of attractions in the early cinema. He pointed out that a sense of “actuality” played a crucial role in films before 1906 and is preponderance over narrative films in terms of production. The Lumière Brother, who according to Gunning created films that engage in “placing the world within one’s reach,” were dedicated to provide the most realistic visual sensations to the spectators. Both <em>Arrival of a Train at La Ciotat</em> (1895) and <em>The Sprinkler Sprinkled</em> (1895) simply filmed as a documentary of everyday scenes, however, audiences were still amazed not virtually because of the narration or the theatrical elements but films’ visibility and the exhibited nature.</p> <div class="l-body"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/coa_1-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/coa_1-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/coa_1-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/coa_1.jpeg"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> <i>Arrival of a Train at La Ciotat</i> </div> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/coa_2-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/coa_2-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/coa_2-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/img4film/coa_2.jpeg"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> <i>The Sprinkler Sprinkled</i> </div> </div> </div> </div> <p>Méliès, born as a magician, had an even deeper uptake of how films could create such illusory moments for occupying spectators’ attention. Méliès never intended to hide his passion for adopting “tricks” in films. His talented editing skills allowed him to add special effects (making heads disappear, a lady suddenly vanish on the stage) freely in the course of production in films like The Four <em>Troublesome Heads</em> (1898) and The Man with <em>The Rubber Head</em> (1901). Along with his clownish performances, Méliès was again able to put on a pompous show to galvanize the crowd’s reaction, but this time in films. In some of his creations, for instance, <em>Voyage to the Moon</em> (1902), he indeed demonstrated traits of plots, adoptions of traditional theatre, and even repeated actions in two successive shots which were thought to be one of the major signs of continuous, logical narration. Gunning, however, was not totally convinced and went ahead argued that the noticeable underlying narrative structures underlay in Méliès’s films were flagged as being of second or third order importance. They served as a framework for Méliès to fully exhibit his magical effects and tricks in front of the crowd, instead of a standalone entity which would possibly alter spectators’ preexisting perception of films. </p> <div class="l-body"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/coa_3-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/coa_3-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/coa_3-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/coa_3.jpeg"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> <i>Voyage to the Moon</i> </div> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/coa_4-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/coa_4-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/coa_4-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/img4film/coa_4.jpeg"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> <i>The Rubber Head</i> </div> </div> </div> </div> <p>Gunning went further and discredited the neglect of the importance of narrative in the early cinemas by accentuated the fact that technology, not film itself was the imposing attraction. With the existence of the kinetograph, and the nascence of more advanced filming technologies, film creators virtually had neither intentions nor motivations to rigorously work on a self-sufficient plot but often left the film projector itself to do all the talking. Gunning likened going to a traditional film theatre in the past to visit a fairground, which people were enthralled by the latest technological marvel and films were just happened to be the medium of display. Exhibitors would even re-edit the originals by adding sound effects, commentaries to maximize spectators’ corporeal pleasures while soliciting the attention of them.</p> <p>Despite impugning early cinema as merely an implement of courting attention from the mass, Cunning did credit the film creators’ endeavor to maintain a holistic narrative structure. Cunning described these efforts as “ambiguous,” and mentioned Porter’s <em>The Great Train Robbery</em> (1903) as an example. While the robbery story accompanied copious violent actions in the film along with the infamous final close up shot of an outlaw firing further reinforced the point on captivating attention of spectators, Gunning acknowledged Porter’s industry for retaining consistency on continuity. In alignment with Cunning, in the book ”Film History, An Introduction”, Thompson and Bordwell also highlighted Porter as one of the forerunners in creating plot-driven and continuous films. Whether was the employments of repeated actions in <em>Life of an American Fireman</em> (1903) adopted from Méliès or the utilizations of crossing cutting he invented in <em>The Great Train Robbery</em>, Porter’s contribution toward the emergence of continuity editing was undeniable. </p> <p>Finally, Gunning gave out his thoughts on the development of cinema by writing down an incisive claim when approaching to the end of the essay — “Every change in film history implies a change in its address to the spectator, and each period constructs its spectator in a new way.”(8)<d-footnote>The Cinema of Attraction: Early Film, Its Spectator and the Avant-Garde by Tom Gunning</d-footnote> Prior to 1906, the film was considered as a tool for wooing attention from the mass not entirely because of its exhibited nature, but also related to the unconsciousness in which people perceived film, as a medium, could achieve. Close-ups, camera movements, and continuity editing, which are ubiquitous in today’s cinema, were seen as avant-garde. As linearity narrative soon became a norm when constructing a standard film, and spectators gradually accustomed to these drastic changes, however, we will see directors like Jean Renoir and Orson Welles, again, pushing the boundary of production and definition of the cinema.  </p>]]></content><author><name>Zejia Chen</name></author><category term="film"/><category term="essay-review"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An excerpt and a reflection about &quot;Cinemas of Attraction&quot; by Tom Gunning]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I was Born, But…</title><link href="https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2020/I-was-Born-But/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I was Born, But…"/><published>2020-11-15T00:02:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-15T00:02:00+00:00</updated><id>https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2020/I-was-Born-But</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zejiachen9912.github.io/blog/2020/I-was-Born-But/"><![CDATA[<div class="l-body"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/i-was-born-but-poster-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/i-was-born-but-poster-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/i-was-born-but-poster-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/i-was-born-but-poster.jpg"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> Although <i>I Was Born, But…</i> (Yasujiro Ozu, 1932) was one of the early works by Ozu, he demonstrates an exceptional aptitude on embodying the callous power dynamics within Japanese working-class structure through the lens of two kids’ growing dismay and perplexity. The film, through a parallel narrative of the father Yoshii (Tatsuo Saito) in work and his children Ryoichi (Hideo Sugawara) and Keiji (Tomio Aoki) in school, presents a keen comparison of the power dynamics of these characters when dealing with convoluted interpersonal relationships.  </div> </div> </div> <h3 id="narrative">Narrative</h3> <p><em>I Was Born, But…</em> revolves around the notion of <strong>power</strong>. For salarymen like Yoshii, all the powers concentrate on the hands of the Iwasaki (Takeshi Sakamoto), the big executive in charge of the firm. In order to receive a good salary, and afford a better life for the family, Yoshii racks his mind to hobnob with his boss. Regardless of the physical locations, he would approach Iwasaki in an adulatory manner whenever he has a chance, to not only physically, but mentally live near the boss. Knowing Iwasaki’s passion for film, Yoshii even participates in Iwasaki’s filming of daily vignettes to cater for his interest, which will later trigger a galling incidence, provoking a series of family dramas. While Ozu revealed a bleak image of underlying hierarchies in the adult world and the hypocritical social fabric embedded in the system, he presented a rather humorous and frisky plot via the scope of the neighborhood children, paralleling with the salaryman script.</p> <p>Unlike the adult world brimming with intrigues and office politics, for children, the advent of power lies in <strong>physical strength</strong>. New to the neighborhood, Ryoichi and Keiji struggle to blend in the new environment, especially when they are intimidated by school bullies, led by a bigger kid (Zentaro Iijima). Luckily, they are wise enough to exploit the physical power of the older delivery boy (Shoichi Kofujita), and eventually to supersede the bigger kid as the most dominant figures in the neighborhood. Even Taro (Katô), Iwasaki’s son, has to pay deference to the boys’ incantation. (a game often played among the children)</p> <div class="l-body"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/iwbb_6-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/iwbb_6-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/iwbb_6-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/iwbb_6.jpeg"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Yoshii participates in the short film produced by his boss </div> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/iwbb_7-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/iwbb_7-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/iwbb_7-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/iwbb_7.jpeg"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Ryoichi &amp; Keiji </div> </div> </div> </div> <p>In the sequence in which the kids witness Yoshii accompanying Iwasaki back home, we finally see these two storylines interweave. Ashamed of the fact that Taro’s father is their father’s boss, Ryoichi and Keiji once again cast the incantation on Toro, hoping to regain at least part of their supremacy. However, Yoshii intervenes and halts the game forthwith, helping Taro gets up from the ground as if he is treating his boss at work at the same time reproaching his sons’ impropriety. Of course, the twins would not understand why their father, an undisputed hero figure in their opinion, would treat Taro in such an obsequious manner. Nevertheless, Father’s reprimand is a blow to the brothers’ imaginary fantasy, offering them a snippet of the how things should work in the reality. The scene puts the two independent worlds under the same frame, revealing adult society’s boot-licking conducts as oppose to children’s ingenuous power ideology and imparting them an imperative lesson about the rigid stratification of the society for the first time. </p> <div class="l-body"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/iwbb_1-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/iwbb_1-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/iwbb_1-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/iwbb_1.png"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> The encounter between the father and the son </div> </div> </div> </div> <h3 id="camera-movement">Camera Movement</h3> <p>Ozu’s deft camera movements usage are inalienable from narrative functions achieved in <em>I Was Born, But…</em> Nonetheless, the most salient visual style ought to be his utilization of camera movements as a medium to navigate between the two major storylines. Reminiscent of Fritz Lang’s employment of sound as a cue to cut between different spaces in M, (Fritz Lang, 1931), Ozu harnessed the tracking of the camera to establish a relationship between two shots regardless of the discontinuous spaces.</p> <p>In the playground/office scene, a sequence of students marching down the playground is cut to the father’s office smoothly as the camera tracks from left to right. The playful camera movement proffers a sense of verisimilitude as audiences mentally follow the camera motion, navigating between the two settings despite the lack of temporal unity. The juxtaposition of irrelevant sequences also puts two drastically different worlds (children and adults) in compare and contrast with each other, soliciting viewers’ examination of the ulterior motifs behind the image. On the playground, the bigger kid got excoriated by the teacher for not following instructions like other students do. In a cut to the next sequence, the camera, however, now tracking from left to right, capturing an associate who meant to concentrate on work, and shifts right forthwith as he could not resist the soporific working environment and began to yawn like anyone else. These nuances in each character’s synchronous motions allude to the social conformity which everyone ought to obey, epitomizing the foreboding transition from carefree children to institutionalized worker for each person living in the society surrounded by sheer competition.</p> <div class="l-body"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/iwbb_2-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/iwbb_2-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/iwbb_2-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/iwbb_2.png"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/iwbb_3-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/iwbb_3-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/iwbb_3-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/iwbb_3.png"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The transition from the playground to the office </div> </div> <h3 id="the-360-degree-system">The 360 Degree System</h3> <p>Although taking immense amounts of inspiration from classical Hollywood comedy, Ozu repeatedly violated the Hollywood continuity editing principle. Instead filming the dialogue scene in the traditional over-the-shoulder method, Ozu framed his dialogue scene more often in a 360-degree style, constantly switching camera positions, proffering a discordant but holistic scene.</p> <p>In the film’s final scene, after understanding the father’s identity and accepting the reality of the life, the two brothers admitted Taro’s father is indeed better. After reconciliation, a straight-on medium long shot shows that the brothers again casting incantation on Taro. In the next shot, however, the camera has already moved behind Ryoichi’s feet, as we observe Taro’s “death” on the ground. At the moment that Ryoichi and Keiji cast the second “revival” incantation in the subsequent shot, the camera has completely switched to the opposite point of view that the initial shot is at, revealing not only the twin brothers but also the train rail barrier. </p> <div class="l-body"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/iwbb_4-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/iwbb_4-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/iwbb_4-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/iwbb_4.png"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/iwbb_5-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/iwbb_5-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/img4film/iwbb_5-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/img4film/iwbb_5.png"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The use of The 360 Degree camera position </div> </div> <p>People would often associate discontinuity film production such as 360-degree system, uncanny camera positions, and playful editing with a sense of distance and detachment because of the diminishing effect on the temporal unity across the narrative. But for Ozu, the combination of these techniques results the opposite, presenting a self-aware and emotionally-intense everyday scenario which builds upon a direct conversation with the audience. The usage of these cinematic techniques continues to be an inextricable part of Ozu’s cinematic language through his entire film career, embodying his philosophy of straddling the realm of subjectivity and objectivity, and offering contemplative cinemas to viewers not only to realize the sadness and melancholy about the reality of life but to retrospect their own experiences.</p>]]></content><author><name>Zejia Chen</name></author><category term="film"/><category term="Japanese-cinema"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A commentary about Yasujiro Ozu's aptitude in parallel narrative structure, cinematography & 360 degree system in the film I was Born, But...]]></summary></entry></feed>